Guide to the John Casper Branner Papers SC0034
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John Casper Branner papers
1882-1925
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922
SC0034
40 Linear Feet
Custodial History note
Received by the University Archives as part of the Stanford Collection, 1965. Additional papers were received in March 2011.
Information about Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography
John Casper Branner, second president of Stanford University, was born in New Market, Tennessee in 1850. He entered Cornell University in 1870, but left in 1874 for Brazil first as assistant geologist on the Geological Survey of Brazil then as assistant engineer for the Sao Cyriaco Gold Mining Company. He returned to Cornell to finish his b.s. degree in 1882. Between 1883 and 1891, he served in a number of state positions including topographic geologist for Pennsylvania and State Geologist of Arkansas; between 1885 and 1891, he also served as professor of geology at Indiana University. The first professor to be named at the new Stanford University in 1891, Branner served as professor of geology at Stanford as well as executive head of the Geology Department. He later served as vice president of Stanford (1898-1913) and president of Stanford (1913-1915) and professor emeritus (1915-1922). He died on March 1, 1922.
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers are Branner's personal and professional papers and do not contain any of his Stanford University Presidential records. The collection contains most of his outgoing and incoming correspondence for the years 1882 to 1921. The outgoing correspondence is in letter press books and has not been indexed. The incoming correspondence has been arranged, but not indexed except for a very few names of importance to Stanford University or of national significance. There is a fairly complete collection of articles and books by Branner as well as manuscripts, photographs, and line drawings of geographical formations; three scrapbooks of earthquake pictures; the report of the Commission investigating the Panama Canal slides; and the manuscript of the Baker genealogy which Branner made. There is a lot of material of interest to geologists and students of the history of geology. While State Geologist of Arkansas Branner refused to encourage speculation concerning gold and silver mines and finally said that there were none of importance, for which he was reviled in many newspapers and hanged in effigy twice. The letters from his field assistants give a rather complete (and amusing) picture of Arkansas in the 1880s. There is also correspondence, mostly during 1906, concerning Branner's dissatisfaction with the U. S. Geological Survey and finally his resignation from it. Branner had many students at Stanford who went on to make quite a reputation as geologists, among them Herbert Hoover and his wife, Lou Henry Hoover. There are many letters from these students from all over the world. Especially interesting are those from the Hoovers and N. F. Drake who were in Tientsin at the time of the Boxer Rebellion. Branner's great interest was Brazil. He had visited Brazil while a graduate student in 1882 and was to make return trips throughout his life. His interests were not purely geological as he also wrote a Portuguese grammar and translated a book on the Portuguese inquisition. A college classmate of his, Ajax J. Lamoureux, lived in Brazil from 1886 to 1906 and his letters give a detailed description of the life there.
Arrangement
Outgoing correspondence arranged chronologically. Incoming correspondence arranged alphabetically.
Geology -- California.; Panama Canal.; San Francisco Earthquake and Fire, Calif., 1906; Geology -- Brazil; Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944; Stanford University. Department of Geology; Lamoureux, Ajax J.; Brazil.; Branner, Susan Kennedy.; Cubberley, Ellwood Patterson; Jordan, David Starr; Drake, N. F.; Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922; United States. Geological Survey.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Hoover, Herbert; Washington, Booker T.
- Correspondence, Series 1
  - Letterpress book, 1883 Aug. -1888 Aug (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letterpress book, 1883 Aug. -1885 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letterpress book, 1885 April -1886 Oct (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letterpress book, 1886 Oct. -1888 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letterpress book, 1887 July -1888 April (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letterpress book, 1888 May -1889 Jan (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letterpress book, 1888 July -1889 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letterpress book, 1889 July -1890 Jan (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letterpress book, 1890 Jan. -1890 May (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letterpress book, 1890 May -1891 March (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letterpress book, 1891 March -1891 Oct (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letterpress book, 1891 Oct. -1892 Sept (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Letterpress book, 1892 Oct. -1893 July (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Letterpress book, 1893 July -1894 Jan (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Letterpress book, 1894 Jan. -1895 Feb (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Letterpress book, 1895 Feb. -1897 March (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Letterpress book, 1897 March 30 -1898 July 11 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Letterpress book, 1898 July 11 -1900 March 5 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Letterpress book, 1900 March 6 -1901 Aug. 6 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Letterpress book, 1901 April -1903 Jan. 10 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Letterpress book, 1903 -1905 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Letterpress book, 1905 -1906 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Letterpress book, 1906 -1907 April (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Letterpress book, 1907 Aug. -1908 Aug (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Letterpress book, 1908 Sept. -1908 Dec (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Letterpress book, 1909 Jan. -1909 May (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Letterpress book, 1909 June -1909 Oct (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Letterpress book, 1909 Nov. -1910 March (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Letterpress book, 1910 April -1910 Aug (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Letterpress book, 1910 Sept. -1911 March (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Letterpress book, 1911 March -1911 Dec (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Letterpress book, 1912 Jan. -1912 June (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Letterpress book, 1912 July -1912 Dec (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Letterpress book, 1913 Jan. -1913 June (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Letterpress book, 1913 July -1913 Dec (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Letterpress book, 1914 Jan. -1914 June (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Letterpress book, 1914 July -1914 Dec (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Letterpress book, 1915 Jan. -1915 June (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Letterpress book, 1915 July -1915 Dec (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Letterpress book, 1916 Jan. -1916 June (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Letterpress book, 1916 July -1916 Dec (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Letterpress book, 1917 Jan. -1917 June (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - Letterpress book, 1917 July -1917 Dec (Box 13, Folder 43)
  - Letterpress book, 1918 Jan. -1918 Dec (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - Letterpress book,., 1919 Jan. -1919 Dec (Box 14, Folder 45)
  - Letters In, 1882 -1887; (bound volume) (Box 14, Folder 46)
  - Letters In, 1882 -1887; (bound volume) (Box 14, Folder 47)
  - Letters In, 1882 -1886; (bound volume) (Box 15, Folder 48)
  - Letters In, 1883 -1887; (bound volume) (Box 15, Folder 49)
  - Letters In A - G, 1887 (Box 16, Folder 50)
    Scope and Contents note
    Most of the letters of 1887 concern the Geological Survey of Arkansas including help from U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey Office; requests for specimen analysis; requests for jobs with G. S. of Arkansas; and the purchase of materials and equipment. Others of note include Clarence H. Esty concerning his desire for a place on the Cornell Board of Trustees; and B. W. Evermann concerning David Starr Jordan and problems at Indiana University.
  - Letters In H - O, 1887 (Box 16, Folder 51)
    Of note: Thomas A. Harden concerning G. S. of Pennsylvania; R. D. Lacoe (G.S. of Penn.) offering to combine forces, Lacoe to work in paleontology; Ed. H. Mathes concerning rich silver ore specimen; and T. C. Mendenhall (Rose Polytechnic Institute) concerning earthquake material.
  - Letters In P - Z, 1887 (Box 16, Folder 52)
  - Letters In A - D, 1888 (Box 16, Folder 53)
  - Letters In E - J, 1888 (Box 16, Folder 54)
    Of note: C. H. Gordon letters pertaining to his summer work with the survey; Wm. F. E. Gurley, 1888 Nov. 11, concerning attack on Branner for his findings by the gold speculators, and 1888 Dec. 9 concerning the Indiana Geological Survey, appointment of State Geologist, and formation of American Geological Society; and O. P. Hay concerning Branner running for State Geologist of Indiana.
  - Letters In K- Q, 1888 (Box 16, Folder 55)
    Of note: E. H. Mathes concerning attacks on Branner; S. E. Meek on summer field experiences; James E. Mills, San Francisco geologist, concerning educational responsibilities of State Geologist.
  - Letters In R - S, 1888 (Box 17, Folder 56)
    Of note: R. R. Rothwell, editor of Engineering and Mining Journal, supporting Branner against his Arkansas critics.
  - Letters In T - Z, 1888 (Box 17, Folder 57)
    Of note: brothers Albert Taff and J. A. Taff on their summer field experiences; and J. L. Wadly, editor of the Daily News of Hot Spring, Arkansas, about fair coverage for the Survey and other matters.
  - Letters In A - B, 1889 (Box 17, Folder 58)
  - Letters In C - D, 1889 (Box 17, Folder 59)
    Of note: W. Albert Chapman on his pamphlet "Brannerite"; T. C. Chamberlin, president of the Univ. of Wisconsin, concerning various geological projects; and Clarence R. Claghorn on his plans for writing a handbook on American mining practices.
  - Letters In E - G, 1889 (Box 17, Folder 60)
    Of note: B. W. Everman concerning the unlikelyhood of his receiving a post as consul to South America; and Leon Griswold giving a full account of summer field work.
  - Letters In H - K, 1889 (Box 17, Folder 61)
    Of note: David Starr Jordan concerning positions in the Geology Department at Indiana University.
  - Letters In L - M, 1889 (Box 18, Folder 62)
  - Letters In N - Q, 1889 (Box 18, Folder 63)
    Of note: R. A. F. Penrose with a full report of his work for Branner.
  - Letters In R - S, 1889 (Box 18, Folder 64)
  - Letters In T - Z, 1889 (Box 18, Folder 65)
  - Letters In A - C, 1890 (Box 18, Folder 66)
  - Letters In D - Greer, 1890 (Box 19, Folder 67)
  - Letters In Griswold - H, 1890 (Box 19, Folder 68)
    Of note: James M. Hamilton letter of support to Branner exposing the "scoundrels" who had attacked him; and Charles Sumner Harmon, 1890 Feb. 27, concerning "Three-Cornered Hat" manuscript translated by Branner.
  - Letters In I - M, 1890 (Box 19, Folder 69)
  - Letters In N - P, 1890 (Box 19, Folder 70)
  - Letters In R- S, 1890 (Box 19, Folder 71)
  - Letters In T - Z, 1890 (Box 20, Folder 72)
  - Letters In A - B, 1891 (Box 20, Folder 73)
  - Letters In C - D, 1891 (Box 20, Folder 74)
  - Letters In E - G, 1891 (Box 20, Folder 75)
  - Letters In H - J, 1891 (Box 21, Folder 76)
    Of note: David Starr Jordan letters describing early Palo Alto, early days at Stanford University, and Branner coming to Stanford.
  - Letters In K - M, 1891 (Box 21, Folder 77)
    Of note: James E. Mills with an analysis of the University and what control the Stanfords could retain.
  - Letters In N - R, 1891 (Box 21, Folder 78)
  - Letters In S - T, 1891 (Box 21, Folder 79)
  - Letters In U - Z, 1891 (Box 21, Folder 80)
  - Letters In A - An, 1892 -1900 (Box 22, Folder 81)
  - Letters In Ap - Az, 1892 -1900 (Box 22, Folder 82)
  - Letters In B - Bien, 1892 -1900 (Box 22, Folder 83)
  - Letters In Bi - Bra, 1892 -1900 (Box 22, Folder 84)
  - Letters In Bra - Butler, 1892 -1900 (Box 22, Folder 85)
  - Letters In Ca - Chism, 1892 -1900 (Box 23, Folder 86)
  - Letters In Cl - Cu, 1892 -1900 (Box 23, Folder 87)
    Of note: E. P. Cubberly, 1897, concerning his work as president of Vincennes and his interest in doing geological work in some Southern California areas.
  - Letters In D - Day, 1892 -1900 (Box 23, Folder 88)
    Of note: George Davidson, U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey, San Francisco, concerning a state survey for California.
  - Letters In De - Di, 1892 -1900 (Box 23, Folder 89)
  - Letters In Do - Dr, 1892 -1900 (Box 23, Folder 90)
    Of note: N. F. Drake, former Branner student, on the Texas Survey, 1894, Stanford, 1897, Ph. D. work in China, 1897, and his return to U. S. in 1900; includes letters written from Tientsin, China, conerning the Boxer Rebellion and relations with the Hoovers, 1899-1900.
  - Letters In Du - Dy, 1892 -1900 (Box 23, Folder 91)
  - Letters In E, 1892 -1900 (Box 24, Folder 92)
    Of note: James P. Eagle, Governor of Arkansas, 1892-1900, concerning the survey and personal matters.
  - Letters In Fag - Fair, 1892 -1900 (Box 24, Folder 93)
  - Letters In Fe - Fu, 1892 -1900 (Box 24, Folder 94)
    Of note: letters from W. M. Fishback, Governor of Arkansas, and G. H. Fitch of the San Francisco Chronicle.
  - Letters In G - Gov, 1892 -1900 (Box 24, Folder 95)
    Of note: Gepp, Rio De Janeiro, Brazil, on life in Brazil.
  - Letters In Gr - Gz, 1892 -1900 (Box 24, Folder 96)
  - Letters In H - Haz, 1892 -1900 (Box 25, Folder 97)
  - Letters In Hen - Hoo, 1892 -1900 (Box 25, Folder 98)
    Of note: Lou Henry [Hoover] on personal matters; E. W. Hilgard, University of California, concerning U.C. and Stanford joining in making a topographical map of the valley areas with federal and state cooperation; Robert Hill, Dept. of Interior, U.S.G.S., concerning Dumble's handling of the Texas G. S. and the reorganization of the U.S.G.S.; and Herbert C. Hoover on his work with the California Geological Survey.
  - Letters In Hop - Hz, 1892 -1900 (Box 25, Folder 99)
    Of note: T. C. Hopkins on paying Hoover $1.75 to pack and ship books to him.
  - Letters In Ha - Hi, 1892 -1900 (Box 25, Folder 100)
    Of note: Lou Henry on her marriage to Herbert Hoover.
  - Letters In Ho - Hz, 1892 -1900 (Box 25, Folder 101)
    Of note: Lou Henry Hoover's letters from Tientsin, China, about their life there.
  - Letters In I - Johnston, 1892 -1900 (Box 25, Folder 102)
  - Letters In Jones, 1892 -1900 (Box 25, Folder 103)
  - Letters In K - Ki, 1892 -1900 (Box 26, Folder 104)
    Of note: extensive correspondence from E. B. Kimball, Stanford class of 1895.
  - Letters In Kl - Law, 1892 -1900 (Box 26, Folder 105)
    Of note: long correspondence of Ajax J. Lamoureux, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, concerning life in Brazil; and Charles Lathrop concerning the opening of a grammar school on the Stanford campus. Attached to Branner's reply to Lathrop, 1899 March 28, is a letter from Jane L. Stanford expressing her wish that there not be one.
  - Letters In L - Lew, 1892 -1900 (Box 26, Folder 106)
  - Letters In Li, 1892 -1900 (Box 26, Folder 107)
  - Letters In M - Maw, 1892 -1900 (Box 26, Folder 108)
  - Letters In Me - Men, 1892 -1900 (Box 26, Folder 109)
    Of note: T. C. Mendenhall, Supt. U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey, concerning controversy about state surveys.
  - Letters In Met - Mit, 1892 -1900 (Box 27, Folder 110)
  - Letters In N - New, 1892 -1900 (Box 27, Folder 111)
  - Letters In N - Per, 1892 -1900 (Box 27, Folder 112)
  - Letters In Ph - Pr, 1892 -1900 (Box 27, Folder 113)
  - Letters In Pu - R, 1892 -1900 (Box 27, Folder 114)
  - Letters In S - Shi, 1892 -1897 (Box 28, Folder 115)
  - Letters In Si - Smy, 1892 -1897 (Box 28, Folder 116)
  - Letters In Sh - Sy, 1892 -1897 (Box 28, Folder 117)
  - Letters In Ta - Td, 1892 -1900 (Box 28, Folder 118)
  - Letters In To - Tu, 1892 -1900 (Box 28, Folder 119)
  - Letters In U - V, 1892 -1900 (Box 28, Folder 120)
  - Letters In W - Way, 1892 -1897 (Box 29, Folder 121)
    Of note: Charles D. Walcott, U.S.C.G. Supt., 1892 Nov. 12, concerning state vs. U.S.G.S. controversy.
  - Letters In We - Will, 1892 -1897 (Box 29, Folder 122)
  - Letters In Will - Winn, 1892 -1897 (Box 29, Folder 123)
    Of note: Bailey Willis, Appalachian division of U.S.G.S., on problem of folding; Newton H. Winchell, managing editor of the American Geologist, regarding the appointment of directors of the U.S.G.S. in 1894.
  - Letters In Wins - Wit, 1892 -1897 (Box 29, Folder 124)
    Of note: Arthur Winslow, Missouri State Geologist, on problems of maintaining the state survey when the state legislature was not enthusiastic.
  - Letters In W - Wa, 1892 -1900 (Box 30, Folder 125)
  - Letters In Wem - Will, 1892 -1900 (Box 30, Folder 126)
  - Letters In Wil - Wood, 1892 -1900 (Box 30, Folder 127)
  - Letters In Wo - Z, 1892 -1900 (Box 30, Folder 128)
  - Letters In, 1892 -1896 (Box 30, Folder 129)
    Most of these letters pertain to the printing of the Arkansas Survey reports; correspondents include R. Ellsworth Call, S. Calvin, T. C. Chamberlin, W. Albert Chapman, and John M. Chase.
  - Letters In Newsom, J. F., 1892 -1896 (Box 30, Folder 130)
  - Letters In Penrose, R. A. F., Jr. and Press Printing Co., 1892 -1896 (Box 30, Folder 131)
  - Letters In A - Arm, 1900 -1903 (Box 31, Folder 132)
    Of note: A. Agassiz, 1903 Dec. 15 regarding Branner's papers on Brazil.
  - Letters In Arn - Az, 1900 -1903 (Box 31, Folder 133)
  - Letters In B - Bey, 1896 -1903 (Box 31, Folder 134)
  - Letters In Bi - Bri, 1896 -1903 (Box 31, Folder 135)
  - Letters In Bro - By, 1896 -1903 (Box 31, Folder 136)
    Of note: Rufus Buck letters from Dawson City, Alaska, 1897-1898, on mining gold in Klondike Country.
  - Letters In C - Chip, 1900 -1903 (Box 31, Folder 137)
  - Letters In Chi - Cu, 1900 -1903 (Box 31, Folder 138)
    Of note: G. A. Clark, 1901 July 31 concerning engineering school taking over public school room at Stanford; and letters by F. L. Cole from Siberia, 1903, and from Korea, 1902, with geological and general descriptions.
  - Letters In D - Du, 1900 -1903 (Box 31, Folder 139)
    Of note: letters from N. F. Drake, 1901-1903, from Shanghai, China, about his work with the Imperial Chinese Railway Administration, with some mention of the Hoovers.
  - Letters In E - G, 1900 -1903 (Box 32, Folder 140)
  - Letters In H - He, 1900 -1903 (Box 32, Folder 141)
  - Letters In Hi - Hu, 1900 -1903 (Box 32, Folder 142)
    Of note: Lou Henry Hoover letters from China and England; and Charles Hodges, 1900 Feb. 26 concerning boarding clubs in the "Camp" on campus and Mrs. Stanford's desire that they not be there.
  - Letters In I - J, 1900 -1903 (Box 32, Folder 143)
    Of note: D. S. Jordan letter with a random mention of the Ross affair.
  - Letters In L - Law, 1900 -1903 (Box 32, Folder 144)
    Of note: letters from Ajax J. Lamoureaux, 1900-1903, on his return to the U. S. after 20 years in Brazil and the book on South American geography that he's writing with Branner.
  - Letters In Le - Lu, 1900 -1903 (Box 33, Folder 145)
  - Letters In M - Me, 1900 -1903 (Box 33, Folder 146)
    Of note: letters from J. A. Means on his experience as a mining consultant in West Africa, Norway, Brazil, and China (with Hoover).
  - Letters In Mi - My, 1900 -1903 (Box 33, Folder 147)
  - Letters In N - O, 1900 -1903 (Box 33, Folder 148)
  - Letters In P - Pri, 1900 -1903 (Box 33, Folder 149)
  - Letters In Pro - Q, 1900 -1903 (Box 33, Folder 150)
  - Letters In R - Rey, 1892 -1903 (Box 34, Folder 151)
  - Letters In Rh - Riz, 1892 -1903 (Box 34, Folder 152)
  - Letters In Ro - Ru, 1892 -1903 (Box 34, Folder 153)
  - Letters In S - Shep, 1896 -1903 (Box 34, Folder 154)
  - Letters In Shi - Su, 1896 -1903 (Box 34, Folder 155)
    Of note: Jane L. Stanford concerning a raise in salary; introduction to Heber Newton; the [Stanford] cemetery not being a public burying grounds; and invitation to Branner, Abott and Stillman to visit her that evening; and T. W. Stanford concerning an opal he sent to Branner.
  - Letters In T - V, 1896 -1903 (Box 35, Folder 156)
  - Letters In W - Wild, 1899 -1903 (Box 35, Folder 157)
  - Letters In Wile- Z, 1899 -1903 (Box 35, Folder 158)
  - Letters In A - B, 1904 -1905 (Box 35, Folder 159)
  - Letters In C - D, 1904 -1905 (Box 35, Folder 160)
  - Letters In E - Hi, 1904 -1905 (Box 36, Folder 161)
  - Letters In Ho - J, 1904 -1905 (Box 36, Folder 162)
  - Letters In K - L, 1904 -1905 (Box 36, Folder 163)
  - Letters In M, 1904 -1905 (Box 36, Folder 164)
  - Letters In N - O, 1904 -1905 (Box 36, Folder 165)
  - Letters In P - Q, 1904 -1905 (Box 36, Folder 166)
  - Letters In R - S, 1904 -1905 (Box 37, Folder 167)
  - Letters In T - Z, 1904 -1905 (Box 37, Folder 168)
  - Letters In A - Ban, 1906 (Box 37, Folder 169)
  - Letters In Bart - [Bz], 1906 (Box 37, Folder 170)
  - Letters In C, 1906 (Box 37, Folder 171)
  - Letters In D - F, 1906 -1907 (Box 38, Folder 172)
  - Letters In G - Hol, 1906 -1907 (Box 38, Folder 173)
  - Letters In Hor - [Hz], 1906 -1907 (Box 38, Folder 174)
  - Letters In I - K, 1906 -1907 (Box 38, Folder 175)
    Of note: a collection of notes and letters from David S. Jordan on the earthquake.
  - Letters In L, 1906 -1907 (Box 38, Folder 176)
  - Letters In L, 1906 -1907 (Box 38, Folder 177)
  - Letters In M - O, 1906 -1907 (Box 39, Folder 178)
  - Letters In P - Q, 1906 -1907 (Box 39, Folder 179)
  - Letters In 1 R, 1906 -1907 (Box 39, Folder 180)
  - Letters In S - T, 1906 -1907 (Box 39, Folder 181)
  - Letters In T - V, 1906 -1907 (Box 39, Folder 182)
  - Letters In W - Z, 1906 -1907 (Box 39, Folder 183)
    Of note: Charles Walcott, director of the U.S.G.S., replying to Branner's attack on the U.S.G.S. and Walcott, 1906 Nov. 9; and several letters on this subject together with Branner's letter of resignation from the U.S.G.S.
  - Letters In A, 1908 -1909 (Box 40, Folder 184)
  - Letters In B, 1908 -1909 (Box 40, Folder 185)
    Of note: Luther Burbank inviting Branner to visit his gardens.
  - Letters In C, 1908 -1909 (Box 40, Folder 186)
  - Letters In D, 1908 -1909 (Box 40, Folder 187)
  - Letters In E - F, 1908 -1909 (Box 40, Folder 188)
  - Letters In G - H, 1908 -1909 (Box 40, Folder 189)
  - Letters In H, 1908 -1909 (Box 40, Folder 190)
    Of note: Herbert Hoover concerning Hoover giving a series of lectures at Columbia, Yale and Stanford.
  - Letters In I - K, 1908 -1909 (Box 41, Folder 191)
  - Letters In L, 1908 -1909 (Box 41, Folder 192)
  - Letters In M, 1908 -1909 (Box 41, Folder 193)
  - Letters In N - O, 1908 -1909 (Box 41, Folder 194)
  - Letters In P, 1908 -1909 (Box 41, Folder 195)
  - Letters In P, 1908 -1909 (Box 41, Folder 195)
  - Letters In R - S, 1908 -1909 (Box 41, Folder 197)
  - Letters In S, 1908 -1909 (Box 41, Folder 198)
  - Letters In T - V, 1908 -1909 (Box 42, Folder 199)
  - Letters In W - Z, 1908 -1909 (Box 42, Folder 200)
  - Letters In A - B, 1910 (Box 42, Folder 201)
  - Letters In C - F, 1910 (Box 42, Folder 202)
  - Letters In G - I, 1910 (Box 42, Folder 203)
  - Letters In J - L, 1910 (Box 42, Folder 204)
  - Letters In M - N, 1910 (Box 43, Folder 205)
  - Letters In O - P, 1910 (Box 43, Folder 206)
  - Letters In S, 1910 (Box 43, Folder 207)
    Of note: letter from Shepley, Rutan and Coolidge, architects, stating that H. H. Richardson had nothing to do with L.S.J.U.; their part in the planning and building, and their exclusion from further planning and building by Mrs. Stanford.
  - Letters In T - Z, 1910 (Box 43, Folder 208)
  - Letters In A - B, 1911 (Box 43, Folder 209)
    Of note; Fred Baker on preparation for collecting trip to Brazil; letter describing Brazilian trip, the building of the railroad.
  - Letters In B, 1911 (Box 43, Folder 210)
  - Letters In C - F, 1911 (Box 43, Folder 211)
  - Letters In G - K, 1911 (Box 44, Folder 212)
  - Letters In L - M, 1911 (Box 44, Folder 213)
  - Letters In N - Q, 1911 (Box 44, Folder 214)
  - Letters In R - S, 1911 (Box 44, Folder 215)
  - Letters In T - Z, 1911 (Box 44, Folder 216)
  - Letters In A - B, 1912 (Box 45, Folder 217)
  - Letters In B, 1912 (Box 45, Folder 218)
  - Letters In C, 1912 (Box 45, Folder 219)
  - Letters In D, 1912 (Box 45, Folder 220)